Guide to the Congo (Democratic Republic) Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Congo (Democratic Republic) collection
1880-2010
MS 1549
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
7.75
(13 boxes)
The collection consists of correspondence, printed material, and photographs relating to the history of Congo (Democratic Republic) and current political, economic, and social conditions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the African Collection Curator.
Associated Materials
African Collection, MS 605; Pamphlet Collection, MS 1351; African Postcard Collection, MS 1575. Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library.
Arrangement
The material in the original accession is arranged chronologically, with photographs last. Additions to the collection may vary in arrangement.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of correspondence, printed material, and photographs relating to the history of Congo (Democratic Republic) and current political, economic, and social conditions.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Access to materials in Accessions 2003-M-047 and 2007-M-018 is by appointment only. Contact the Head of Public Services or the Public Services Manager.
Belgium -- Foreign relations -- Congo (Democratic Republic); Congo (Democratic Republic) -- Description and travel; Congo (Democratic Republic) -- Economic conditions; Congo (Democratic Republic) -- Foreign relations -- Belgium; Congo (Democratic Republic) -- Politics and government; Katanga (Congo); Lantern slides; Photographs -- Congo (Democratic Republic); Schweitzer, Albert, 1875-1965
- Original Accession, 1885-1993
  - Marquess of Salisbury: correspondence to the King of the Belgians concerning his rule over the Belgian Congo, 1885 November 25 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Résumé de la Campagne Arabe," by unidentified author, [1894?] (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "Le Salut des Troupes Coloniales Belges à ceux du Pays envahi": aerial propoganda leaflet dropped over German occupied Belgium, 1917 October (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "Travel in the Belgian Congo: Bulletin of Useful Information with Map of Principal Communications," Office National du Tourisme de Bélgique, 1939 January (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "Diario Popular 14-10-1942," introduction to The Volcanoes, by Sake (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Agricultural/technological development: reports, pamphlets, proceedings from conferences, 1945, 1970, 1988-1990 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Centre d'Information et de Documentation du Congo Belge et du Ruanda-Urundi: booklets, 1953, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - L'Union des Femmes Coloniales: bulletin, 1954 January (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Houser, George: letter describing visit to Albert Schweitzer's hospital at Lamborene and related topics, 1954 September 23 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Economy/banking: magazines, bulletins, 1957, 1973, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Belgian writings on the Congo: commentaries, speeches, booklets, 1960-1969 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Gullion, Edmund A., U.S. Ambassador to the Republic of Congo: radio interview, 1961 December 3 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - "Katanga, 11th July 1960 - 11th July 1962": speech by President Tshombe, 1962 July 11 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - "The UN in Katanga: the futile deaths"; Katangese Ministry of Information, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Mouvement Populaire de la Revolution (MPR): manifestos, resolutions, 1967, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Magazines, 1971, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - La Voix des Forces Armées Zaïroises: Bimensuel de la Défense Nationale, 1972 October 15 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Mbegu: Revue Pédagogique et Culturelle, Institut Superior Pédagogique, Université Nationale du Zaïre, 1978 December (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - "Licho": bulletin du Campus de Lubumbashi, 1980 June (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Institut Makanda Kobobi: booklets, journals, 1981-1984 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Newspapers, 1981-1993 (Box 1, Folder 21 - 22)
  - Newspapers, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Congolese National Liberation Front (FLNC): posters by and about, 1983, undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Martens, Ludo, Party of Labour of Belgium (Marxist-Leninist): articles, papers, printed materials, 1988, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - U.S.-Congo Friendship Committee: articles, newsletters, pamphlets, [1988?]-1989, undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Revue du Travail: Revue Zaïroise du Travail de Parution Trimestrielle, 1989 January (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Ancien Élu du Peuple et Membre du Collège des Fondateurs de l'U.D.P.S.: lettre ouverte au Gouverneur du Shaba contre le massacre des étudiants au Campus de Lubumbashi, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - "Zari Bulletin," Zaire-American Research Institute, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Milango, H. E. M. Andre, Head of Government at the Law School of Yale University: statement before the United Nations, Mission Permanente de la République du Congo, 1991 December 5 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - La Conscience: Organe Chrétien Indépendant, 1992 April (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - "Congo, Yesterday and Today: A background of 80 years of ruthless exploitation in the Congo": publication of The Bureau of African Affairs, undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - "Victoria Falls": photograph album, [1915?] (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - The Belgian Congo: photographs with identifying material, Congopresse, 1936-1949 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Photographs with subtitles and text, undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - "Le Programme Social de la Main d'Oeuvre Indigène," L'Illustration Congolaise, 1928 April 1 (Folder 3)
- Additional Material, 1909-1995; Accession 1995-M-206
  - Additional printed materials, 1909, 1970-1995, undated (Box 1)
- Additional Material, 1966-1997; Accession 2000-M-040
  - Additional printed materials, [includes proverbs and stories in the Tetela language, 1966], 1966, 1993-1997 (Box 1)
- Additional Material, 1993; Accession 2002-M-072
  - Newspapers [fourteen; various titles], 1993 (Box 1)
- Additional Material, 1900; Accession 2003-M-047
  Conditions Governing Access
  Access to materials in Accessions 2003-M-047 and 2007-M-018 is by appointment only. Contact the Head of Public Services or the Public Services Manager.
  - Glass slides of the Congo [Underwood & Underwood, Geography Units, all thirty scenes are identified], [1900?] (Box 1)
- Additional Material, 1941-2001; Accession 2004-M-034
  - Amnesty International [report on the torture of students], 2001 June (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Le Congo: Documents", 1956, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Kinshasa I, II, [general information], 2000 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Newspapers
    - L'Echo du Kivu, 1941 December (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - L'Avenir Colonial Belge, 1943 November (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Additional Material, 1909?-2003; Accession 2005-M-116
  - ASADHO/KATANGA (African Association for the Defense of Human Rights) [press releases], 2003 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - The Cromwell Crusader, no. 1, "Cocoa Slavery Edition", [1909?] (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "MOKANDA, La Lettre," no. 6 [newsletter], 1983 December (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Mouvement Ouvrier et Paysan du Congo (Zaire) [statements of opinion/policy], 1991 October 3, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "Les Transports Ferroviaires en Afrique Centrale," Le D éfi in (UDEAC), no. 6, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - UNEZ (Union Nationale des Etudiants Zaïrois), 1984 April (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Additional Material, 1880-1909; Accession 2007-M-018
  - Hand-colored lantern slides of the Congo, [188-]-[190-] (Box 1)
- Additional Material, 1961-1962; Accession 2008-M-014
  - Les Martyrs de Kongolo, 1962 January (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Photographs
    - Album of forty photographs depicting casualties in Katanga Province, 1961 September-October (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Photograph of microscopists searching for cure of sleeping sickness (a disease prevalent in diamond mine workers), Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Photograph of native soldiers, Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Additional Material, 1961-2006; Accession 2011-M-030
  Arrangement
  Materials are arranged as received.
  - Magazines
    - Kivu, Republic of Zaire, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Lettres Zaïroises, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Voici le Zaïre, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Zaïre (L'Hebdomadaire de l'Afrique Centrale), 1978 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Supplément au Périodique des Droits de l'Homme, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Institut National de la Statistique: Analyse de l'Inflation a Lubumbashi, 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - The UN and the Congo, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Ngonge: Carnets d'Histoire et de Littérature Kongo, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - JV Magazine, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Mampinga, 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Le Curieux, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Journals
    - Reflexions: Révue Philosophique de Bamanya, 1984 June (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Revue Congolaise du Travail, !971 April (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Elimu, 1981 January-March (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Jana Na Kesho: Revue des Etudiants du Département d'Histoire, 1984 Mar, 1986 April (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Voix Muntu: Revue Culturelle et Scientifique, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - The Thinker, English Club, University of Lubumbashi, 1981 December-1982 January (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Cahiers d'Actualité Sociale, 1984 July (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - La Messagère 5, University of Lubumbashi, 1982 May-June (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Newspapers
    - Mosali, 1979 January 15 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Salongo, 1981 May 20 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Taifa, 1984 July 20, August 30 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - La Sagesse, 1991 July 30 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - L'Unité, 1991 August 7 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - La Tribune, 1990 November 29 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Espoir, 1991 August 12 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Umoja, 1991 July 29 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Nukta, no. 22, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Mukuba, 1991 August 16 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - ASADHO/Katanga: Communiqué de presse, Nos. 14-17, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Centre des Droits de l'Homme et du Droit Humanitaire CDH: Communiqué de presse, 2004 October 29 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - What Are We Doing in the Congo?, Dr. Hyman Lumer, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Additional material, 1927-2010; Accession 2015-M-001
  - Printed material, 1927-2010 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)